<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters Patent of Henry VIII Establishing Christ College and Church, Brecon,
                Wales</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
            <!-- Trying this out with multiple witnesses to see how it works -->
            <msDesc>
                <!-- This is witness C: where to indicate that? -->
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <repository>St John's College</repository>
                    <idno>MS. H.12</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="SC">
                        <!-- what does this type SC mean? -->
                        <idno>279</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem>
                        <title>Statutes of St Davids</title>
                        <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                    </msItem>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                </msContents>
                <physDesc>
                    <p>
                        <material>Paper</material>: ff iii + 265 pp + ff xi. Cover 25 cm x 37.7 cm;
                        pages 23.5 cm x 36.5 cm; ruled area 17.2 cm x 31.7 cm. Brown soft leather
                        cover, but red soft leather spine; pencil note inside back cover reads
                        “Re-backed &amp; repaired by J. P. Gray May 1972 for £7.50.” Written in one
                        clear hand throughout, similar but not identical to main hand of D, with
                        annotations in the hand of Thomas Baker and one or more others.</p>
                </physDesc>
                <provenance>
                    <p>Given to College by Bishop Thomas Watson of St Davids (bishop 1687-1699), a
                        benefactor of the College (Yardley, _Menevia Sacra_ pp. 118-19, 384).
                        Written <origDate>before 1717, when Watson died, and possibly before 1699,
                            when he was deprived of his bishopric.</origDate> Remains in Old Library
                        at St Johns College. Consulted by Yardley in compiling _Menevia Sacra_
                        (1739-1770); page numbers align with those given in his digest of the
                        statutes (National Library of Wales, SDCh/B/31).</p>
                </provenance>
            </msDesc>

            <msDesc>
                <!-- This is witness D: where to indicate that? -->
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                    <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                    <idno>SDCh/B/23</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem>
                        <title>Statutes of St Davids</title>
                        <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                    </msItem>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                </msContents>
                <physDesc>
                    <p>
                        <material>Paper</material>: ff. ii + 181 pp + ff?. Pages 26.5 cm x 41 cm;
                        writing area 18.4 cm x 36.5 cm. Brown leather cover. Written in one clear
                        hand throughout, similar but not identical to main hand of C, with
                        annotations in one or more other hands.</p>
                </physDesc>
                <provenance>
                    <p>Note in pen on f. ii r: "It appearing by an Attestation wrote over against
                        the first Page of the Statute-Book of this Cathedral Church [now N.L.W.,
                        SDCh/B/22] that in the year 1719 the said Statute-Book was collated by the
                        late Bishop Ottley &amp; the late Mr. Chantor Davies with a much more
                        ancient manuscript of the said Statutes [now British Library, Harley MS
                        6280], which was attested A[nn]o 1588 by Bishop Middleton, Chantor Huett
                        &amp; c., &amp; which said ancient Copy has ever since been unfortunately
                        missing (which is greatly lamented) or at least was never seen by any of the
                        present members of the Chapter; -Richard Davies Archdeacon of St. Davids
                        &amp; one of the Canons Residentiary of this Church made many Enquiries with
                        various Persons and in various places, in order to the recovering, if
                        possible, the said ancient manuscript: and particularly haveing procured
                        diligent search to be made for that purpose among the Books and Papers of
                        the said late Mr. Chantor Davies, altho' the Book in question could not,
                        upon such serch, be found, yet the present manuscript (containing not only
                        the St. Davids Statutes, but also the Patent of King Henry the Eighth for
                        founding Christ's College in Brecon) being met with among the said Books,
                        was, at the Request of the said Archdeacon, generously made a Present of to
                        the Chantor and Chapter of St. Davids by the Reverend Mr. Richard Davies
                        Master of Arts, Golden Prebendary of this Church [NB he held the preb. of
                        Mathrey, alias the Golden Prebend, form 1723 to his d. in May 1746], on
                        order to be laid up in the Chapter-Chest of this Cathedral, where it is
                        accordingly deposited this 25th day of July in the Year one thousand seven
                        hundred and forty eight by me Richard Davies Archdeacon of St. Davids."
                        [pencil note below:] "Qu. whether this is in the British Museum."
                            <origDate>Before 14 Dec. 1732</origDate>, when Precentor (Chantor) John
                        Davies died. Remains in the legal ownership of the Dean and Chapter of St
                        Davids; placed on deposit at National Library of Wales.</p>
                </provenance>
            </msDesc>

            <msDesc>
                <!-- This is witness O: where to indicate that? -->
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>British Library</repository>
                    <idno>Harley MS 1249</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem>
                        <title>Statutes of St Davids</title>
                        <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                    </msItem>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                </msContents>
                <physDesc>
                    <p>
                        <material>Paper</material>: pp/ff??. Cover 25cm x 38 cm; pages about 23.5 x
                        36.5; writing frame 16.5 x 33. Not ruled. Red cover, buckram with leather
                        spine and corners. Written in one clear hand throughout.</p>
                </physDesc>
                <provenance>
                    <p>Origin unknown. Two letters are pasted in among foreleaves. One from Bishop
                        Adam Ottley (bishop of St Davids 1713-23) mentions borrowing a copy of the
                        Statutes from Robert Harley, 1st Earl of Oxford, though this may in fact
                        refer to the MS that is now Harley 6280, which Ottley used to check National
                        Library of Wales, MS SDCh/B/22 in 1719. The other is from his successor,
                        Richard Smallbrook (bishop of St Davids 1724-1731) in 1729, promising to
                        return to Edward Harley, 2nd Earl of Oxford, a copy of the statutes (either
                        Harley 6280 or this present volume) which he had borrowed to use in a suit
                        in the Court of Arches to oblige canons of St Davids to residence. Harley
                        6280 was in the hands of Thomas Baker at Cambridge at some unknown date
                        between 1719 and his death in 1740 (Bodleian Library, Willis MS. 38 f.
                        531r-v), and it may be that Harley 1249 was thus the only copy Harley had to
                        lend to Smallbrook at this time. <origDate>Probably before 1729.</origDate>,
                    </p>
                </provenance>
            </msDesc>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
