<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xml>
    <timeline>
        <heading>List of important dates</heading>
    
    <entry when="1269"> Dominican Friars establish a priory at Brecon, Breconshire. </entry>
    <entry when="1283"> Bishop Thomas Bek of St Davids establishes a collegiate church at Llangadog, Carmarthenshire.</entry>
    <entry when="1287"> Bek moves his new Llangadog foundation to Abergwili, Carmarthenshire, on the outskirts of the town of Carmarthen.</entry>
    <entry when="1509"> Henry VIII crowned King.</entry>
    <entry when="1534"> Henry VIII breaks with Rome; King declared 'Supreme head on earth of the Church of England'.</entry>
    <entry when="1536"> William Barlow made Bishop of St Davids; monasteries dissolved; first act incorporating Wales into the English state.</entry>
    <entry when="1538"> Houses of friars dissolved, including the Dominican house at Brecon.</entry>
    <entry from="1539" to="1540">Barlow writes to Thomas Cromwell, proposing that Abergwili Collegiate Church be re-founded at Brecon and St Davids Cathedral be re-founded at Carmarthen.</entry>
    <entry when="1541"> Henry VIII issues Letters Patent moving Abergwili Collegiate Church to Brecon under the new name Christ College Brecon. Copy recorded in the Patent Rolls (Witness R).</entry>
    <entry when="1543"> Second act incorporating Wales into the English state.</entry>
    <entry from="1561" to="1567"> Bishop Richard Davies of St Davids and William Salesbury collaborate at Abergwili to translate the Anglican Book of Common Prayer and New Testament into Welsh.</entry>
    <br/>        
    <entry from="1680" to="1740"> Witnesses C, D, I, and O written: all are copies of the medieval Statutes of St Davids Cathedral, to which the Brecon charter appears as an appendix. Copies circulate, ending up at St Davids (D and I), St John's College Cambridge (C), and the Harley Collection (O).</entry>
    <entry when="1719"> Browne Willis publishes the Brecon charter in <em>An History of the Mitred Parliamentary Abbies, and Conventual Cathedral Churches</em>, vol. II (Witness W).</entry>
    <entry from="1739" to="1761"> Edward Yardley, Archdeacon of Carmarthen, compiles his history of St Davids Cathedral and Diocese, <em>Menevia Sacra</em>.</entry>
    </timeline>
    
   
</xml>

